Guide to the Communications Workers of America Photographs and Videos PHOTOS.086
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America Photographs and Videos
1915-1995
1960-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America
Rairdon, Horace
PHOTOS.086
11.25 Linear Feet in 8 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, 5 oversize folders, 1 photograph box, and 5 flat-file folders
The Communications Workers of America (CWA) was founded in 1947 as an industrial union of telephone industry workers. This collection documents the union's activities, including strikes and national conventions, through photographic prints, slides, a scrapbook, and videos.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Communications Workers of America donated photographs and records in a series of accessions starting in 1995; addtiional materials were added periodically. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1987.011, NPA.2000.061, NPA.2000.038, NPA.2003.001, NPA.2003.005, NPA.2003.109, NPA.2005,007, NPA.2005.061, NPA.2006.064, NPA.2006.066, 2018.011, and 2018.024.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in four series. Series I has been further arranged into subseries; the contents of each subseries are arranged chronologically with the except of Subseries IL, which has been arranged alphabetically. Series II-IV are unprocessed and have not been arranged by an archivist. The series and subseries arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I: Photographic Prints, 1915-1988.
Subseries IA: Bargaining.
Subseries IB: Convenctions, Conferences, and Meetings.
Subseries IC: Group Photographs.
Subseries ID: Political/Legislative.
Subseries IE: Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades.
Subseries IF: Union Activities.
Subseries IG: International.
Subseries IH: Union Officers.
Subseries II: Technology and Workplace.
Subseries IJ: Oversized Photographs.
Subseries IK: Beatrice Smith Photographs.
Subseries IL: Addendum.
Series II: Slides, circa 1915-1986.
Series III: Horace Rairdon Scrapbook, circa 1940-1975.
Series IV: Videos, 1985-1995.
Folders are arranged chronologically within subject series.
Organized into 12 subseries:
Historical/Biographical Note
The Communications Workers of America (CWA), founded in 1947 as an industrial union of telephone industry workers, was the culmination of nearly a half-century of struggle for telephone unionism. Its first president was Joseph A. Beirne, who had led its predecessor union, the National Federation of Telephone Workers (NFTW), in an organizing campaign and a nation-wide strike in 1946 that resulted in the first national agreement with the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T).
During the next twenty-five years under the leadership Beirne, the CWA moved aggressively to organize all the telephone workers in the United States. It was not until 1974, however, after years of labor-management unrest and a series of strikes, that AT&T agreed to system-wide collective bargaining. Shortly after the national contract was signed, Joseph Beirne died and was replaced as President by Secretary-Treasurer Glenn E. Watts. In the 1960s, the CWA became an active participant in international labor activities supporting the United States government's Cold War policies through the union's involvement in organizations such as the CIA- and USAID (United States Agency for International Development)- financed American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD).
In the 1980s the CWA began to expand beyond telecommunications, creating a Public Employees Department that successfully organized 34,000 New Jersey state workers in 1981. In 1985 Morton Bahr became the CWA President. In 1987 the CWA merged with the International Typographical Workers Union. In 1992 it absorbed the National Association of Broadcast Employees and the Newspaper Guild merged with the CWA. By the 2000s the CWA had become one of the United States' largest and strongest unions with more than 600,000 members.
Other Finding Aids
A description of individual photographs in Subseries IA-IJ is available in the reading room.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 1151 Records (WAG 244)
Records of Communications Workers of America (WAG 124)
Records of Communications Workers of America, Addendum (WAG 124.1)
Communications Workers of America, District 1 Records (WAG 117)
Communications Workers of America, District 2 Records (WAG 218)
Eleanore Collins Papers (WAG 089)
Scope and Content Note
Communications Workers of America Photographs and Videos consists of photographic prints, slides, a scrapbook, and videos, mostly from the 1960s through the 1980s. Most materials are images documenting union activities, including national conventions, congresses, bargaining, strikes, demonstrations, members at work, and changes in telecommunications technology. The scrapbook contains union ephemera in addition to photographs. Videos date from the late 1980s and early 1990s and document conventions and other union activities.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Black-and-white photographs.; Women employees -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Telephone operators.; Photographic prints.; Telecommunication -- Employees -- United States.; Labor unions and international relations -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Slides (photographs); Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Color slides.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Videocassettes.; Beirne, Joseph A., 1911-; Bahr, Morton; American Institute for Free Labor Development; Association of Communications Equipment Workers; Werkau, Carlton W.; Watts, Glenn E.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; United States. Agency for International Development; Smallwood, William; National Federation of Telephone Workers; Knecht, Louis; International Typographical Union; Hackney, Ray; American Telephone and Telegraph Company -- Employees
- Series I: Photographic Prints, 1915-1988; 1960-1988; 4.25 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, 2 oversize folders, and 1 flat file folder
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Photographic Prints consists of approximately 4,300 prints--mainly 8x10" black and white photographs, with a small number of 3x4" and 3x5" black and white snapshots. Most of the images date from the 1960s to the 1980s. A handful, drawn from the records of predecessor or related earlier unions (some of which merged with the CWA) such as the International Typographical Union (ITU), Association of Communications Equipment Workers (ACEW), and National Federation of Telephone Workers (NFTU), date from the1910s, 1920s, and 1930s (many of these may be found in the Oversized Photographs series). Photographs of CWA President Joseph A. Beirne and his family, other union officers, CWA conventions, conferences and meetings, and other union activities (including organizing, dinners, receptions and the union's support for scholarships and charities) dominate the collection. Through images of their officers and members, locals from across the country are represented, including those from Alabama, California, Florida, Georgia, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, Louisiana, Michigan, Minnesota, Mississippi, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, South Carolina, Tennessee, Virginia, reflecting a strong southern regional presence.
  A large portion of the collection (its single largest series) also documents the union's international activities, through images showing its officers attendance at international conferences of telephone workers and allied unions in Europe, Asia and the South Pacific, Latin America, and international labor, as well as visits by representatives of foreign unions to United States. These international images reflect the union's involvement in Cold War politics through its friendly relationships with the CIA- and USAID (United States Agency for International Development)- financed American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD), with labor unions in South Vietnam, and exiled Cuban labor unions.
  Also well-represented are images showing the union's close relationships with leading American politicians, officials, and political figures (mainly Democratic) through photographs of CWA leaders posed with most of the sitting United States Presidents from Truman through Carter, Vice President Hubert H. Humphrey, Eleanor Roosevelt, Arthur Goldberg, and Dean Rusk, members of Congress including Senators John F., Robert F., and Edward M. Kennedy, Kefauver, Mondale, Morse, and members of the House of Representatives, including both (then-Congressmen) Richard Nixon and John F. Kennedy; Andrew Young, and Thomas "Tip" O'Neill, as well as with labor leaders such as George Meany and Walter Reuther. Occasionally a celebrity from outside the worlds of politics and labor makes an appearance, such as actors and comedians Charleton Heston, Bob Hope, Jerry Lewis, and Linda Lavin. A smaller, but significant number of images document bargaining, strikes, demonstrations, and parades, members at work (mainly female telephone operators), and changes in telecommunications technology.
  Many photographs have captions, dates, and identifications of persons written on their reverse sides. Individual photographs or groups of photographs have been assigned unique numbers or number/letter combinations, which are written inside square brackets on the back of each print.
  - Subseries IA: Bargaining.
    - Bargaining (Includes John J. Moran, President of the Federation of Long Lines Telephone Workers), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bargaining, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bargaining, 1971-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bargaining, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries IB: Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings.
    - Campaigns and Conventions, circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings (Includes images of Affiliation Committee, with Beatrice Smith, 1949; Horace Rairdon), 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings (Includes Glenn Watts; Gus Cramer; J.W. Webb), 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings (Includes Bayard Rustin), 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings 1987 (Includes Pete Catucci of Local 2336; Morton Bahr; James Booe of CWA District 9; actress Linda Lavin), 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings (Includes Gus Cramer, Marvin Collins, and Philip Murray), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Conventions, Conferences, and Meetings, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - District 9, Local 9407 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Subseries IC: Group Photographs.
    - Group Photographs (Includes Marie Mengersow, and images of the Casino Royale Restaurant, Washington, DC ), 1937-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Group Photographs (Includes Glenn Watts, Michael M. Horn), 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Group Photographs (Includes images of Herman Pirchner's Alpine Village, Cleveland's Theater Restaurant, Playhouse Square, Cleveland Ohio), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Group Photographs (Includes John J. Moran; District 2 women, Dot Early and Lou Sobar; Gus Cramer; Beverly Stone; Hal Sisson; Joseph Beirne; officers of the Federación Sindical de Trabajadores Telefónicos de Cuba (Federation of Telephone Workers of Cuba) aka FSTTC; officials of the American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD)), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries ID: Political/Legislative.
    - Political/Legislative (Includes President Harry S. Truman; Joseph Beirne; Congressman John F. Kennedy; Senator Wayne Morse; Walter Reuther; Eleanor Roosevelt; Senator Estes Kefauver), 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Political/Legislative (Includes Senator Dee Huddleston (KY); President John F. Kennedy; AFL President William Green; Congressional hearing on illegal wiretapping (1962); Hubert Humphrey; George L.P. Weaver, US Assistant Secretary of Labor (for International Affairs); Secretary of State Dean Rusk; Glenn Watts; J. W. Webb; Adlai Stevenson; and John Gronouski (U.S. Ambassador to Poland); Senator John (?) McCormack Robert F. Kennedy), 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Political/Legislative (Includes Joseph Beirne; President Harry S. Truman, Senator Edward Kennedy, Ray Hackney; Joseph D. Keenan; meeting of the National Labor Committee for McGovern and Shriver, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Political/Legislative (Includes President Richard Nixon; Senator Walter Mondale; President Jimmy Carter; Representative Andrew Young (D-GA); Senator Edward Kennedy; Representative Claude Pepper; George Meany; E. Fertig, CWA District 2; James B. Booe; Glenn Watts), 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Political/Legislative (Includes Richard Nixon (young); Morton Bahr with Senator Edward Kennedy; Walter Mondale; President Harry Truman; President Lyndon Johnson; NY Gov. Hugh Carey; President Eisenhower; Arthur Goldberg; Ray Hackney; William Doherty, Sr. (President of the U.S. Letter Carriers Union); William Doherty, Jr. (Inter-American Representative of the Post, Telegraph and Telephone Workers International (PTTI) and Social Projects Director, American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD); Senator Abraham Ribicoff; President John Kennedy, Senator Hubert Humphrey; Walter Reuther; George Meany; Rosalind Carter; President Jimmy Carter; Glenn Watts; Senator G. Mennen Williams; Mary O'Hara (CWA District 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries IE: Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades.
    - Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades, 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades, 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - CWA's "National Job Pressures Day" Campaign Includes William C. Evitt (Local 2201, Albuquerque, NM); members/officers of Mountain Bell Local 8611), Jun 15, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades (Includes members of CWA Local 195 and International Federation of Professional and Technical Engineers (IFPTE), 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Strikes, Demonstrations, and Parades (Includes Marty Hughes; Nita Moss (Traffic Local 4307), 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Subseries IF: Union Activities.
    - Union Activities, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Union Activities, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Union Activities (Includes Joseph Beirne; Congressman Roman Pucinski; Vi Bogan; Glenn Watts), 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Union Activities (Includes Dave Lucas of Local 7120; President, J. E. Dose of Local 7112; Erma Wiszmann of Local 7117; President; Ed Wallace, California Apprenticeship Program), 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Union Activities (Includes Ray Hackney; Grace Lee Mayer, Mary Williamson; Coralean Capps; Marilee Beiderman), undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Union Activities (Includes images of CWA organizing against Teamster Union raids; Annual Kiddies' Christmas Party), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Subseries IG: International.
    - International: General, 1950, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Asia: General (Includes CWA and Tunisian Labor Study Team; with Ray Hackney; J ohn Crull; Mrs. Anne Beirne; Mr. V. S. Mathur,, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU); Joseph Beirne; Miss Maniben Kara, Western Railway Employees' Union (of India); organizers and officials of the Federation of National P&T Organisations (of India), undated, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Asia: Japan(Includes meetings with Zendentsu (Japan Telecommunications Union) in Washington, DC and Japan; Akira Yamagishi (President of Zendentsu); members of Zentai (Japan Postal Workers Union); Ray Hackney; John Crull; Mike Florentino, of Local 1180); Morton Bahr), 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Asia: Philippines (Includes Innocencio "Peter" Ferrer; General Carlos P. Romulo; Ken Hutchinson; Ramon Jimenez, Daisy B. Atienza, and Ben Gonzalez of Asian Labor Education Center), 1962, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Asia: Vietnam (Includes Glenn Watts; leader and representatives of the Telecommunications Workers' Union of South Vietnam), 1965, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Caribbean: General, 1961, 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Caribbean: Costa Rica (Includes 5th Postal Telegraph and Telephone International; (PTTI) Inter-American Congress; Joseph Beirne; Glenn Watts;Wallace Legge), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Caribbean: Cuba(Includes officers and members of Federación Sindical de Trabajadores Telefónicos de Cuba (aka Federation of Telephone Workers of Cuba aka FSTTC), in Cuba and in exile in the United States, training with American Institute for Free Labor Development (AIFLD); Joseph Beirne; Ray Hackney), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Caribbean: Guyana (Includes officers of British Guiana Post Office Workers Union, President Andrew L. Jackson; Yvette Braithwaite; Neville E. Griffith; Selwyn O. Felix; Samuel I. Carmichael, Rudolph A. Smith; guests attending independence celebration for Guyana (formerly British Guiana): U.S. State Department officials, Joseph Beirne, William Doherty (President of the U.S. Letter Carriers Union), officers of Postal Telegraph and Telephone International [PTTI]), undated, 1962, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Europe: England, 1956, 1963, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Europe: France, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Europe: Germany, 1962, 1965-1966, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Latin America: General (Includes leaders of Latin American unions affiliated with Postal Telegraph and Telephone International [PTTI] at CWA Training Center, Front Royal, Virginia; Carl Tull (Communications Workers Association of Trinidad and Tobago); Ray Hackney, Wallace Legge; Joseph Beirne), undated, 1959, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mexico, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Middle East: Israel Israel (Includes Shimon Peres; Golda Meier; Histadrut meeting; Morton Bahr; Joseph and Anne Beirne, Wallace Legge, Walter Reuther and Mrs. Reuther), undated, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - New Zealand, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - South America: Argentina (Includes Joseph Beirne with others arriving for inauguration of new Argentinian president, Dr. Arturo Illía), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - South America: Brazil (Includes Ray Hackney and Joseph Beirne meeting with Brazilian Telephone Workers union; training of the Brazilian Postal Telephone and Telegraph Workers under auspices of the United States Agency for International Development), undated, 1963, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - South America: Columbia (Includes meetings of Postal Telegraph and Telephone International [PTTI] held in Bogota), 1960, 1963, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - South America: Ecuador (Includes Congress of Telecommunications Workers of Ecuador [FENETEL] Congress: Ray Hackney, Wallace Legge (Inter-American Representative of ICTT [Internationale du Personnel des Postes, Telegraphes, et Telephones [International Union of Workers of Postal Telegraph and Telephone Workers); William Doherty, Jr. [PTTI representative]; SenatorVice-President Hubert Humphrey), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - South America: Peru (Includes meeting with Peruvian Radio Operators and Telegraphers' Association, Lima; Glenn Watts; and Manuel Peña Prado [Peruvian Telecommunications Union]), 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - South America: Venezuela (Includes visit of Federation of Telecommunications Workers of Venezuela [FETRATEL] representatives to CWA headquarters in Washington, DC; Glenn Watts, J. W. Webb, and L. E. Moore), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Subseries IH: Union Officers.
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family (Includes Joseph Beirne presenting award to comedian Bob Hope), 1946-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family (Includes Joseph Beirne, Raymond Percle [CWA Local 3412, Thibodeaux, LA], Louis E. Moore, Alva Moore, Charles Wood, M. Nyrtue, Charles Wheeler [Program Director for Bolivia and Peru for American Institute for Free Labor Development]), 1962-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family (Includes "CWA Membership Meeting of the Air" TV program; comedian Jerry Lewis; Joseph Beirne; Glenn Watts), 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family (Includes Joseph Beirne on WFMY-TV; and Beirne and Charlton Heston), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Joseph A. Beirne and family, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Morton Bahr (Includes: Bahr with President George Bush, 1990, and International Typographical Union [ITU]President Robert McMichen signing CWA-ITU merger agreement), 1987, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ray Hackney, undated, 1952-1957, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Louis Knecht (Includes George Miller), undated, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - William Smallwood, undated, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Glenn E. Watts (Includes Richard W. Hackler; Paul Gray (District 12); D.L. McCowen (District 6)), 1965-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - C. W. "Slim"Werkau, undated, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Officer Photos (Includes Martha Murrill [Local 2110, Maryland (?)]; William M. Dunn [Cincinnati Federation of Telephone Workers]; John L. Crull; James Massey; Lena Wicks), 1944, 1957, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Group Photos (Includes first Executive Board and officers of the: National Federation of Telephone Workers [NFTW]: C. W. Werkau; Joseph Bierne; Jake Schacht; Pansy Harris; [Beatrice?] Smith; Paul Griffith; Bert Horth; "Jack" Moran), 1939-1957 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries II: Technology and Workplace.
    - Technology and Workplace, 1966-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Technology and Workplace, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Women, undated, 1924, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Subseries IJ: Oversized Photographs.
    - Oversize Group Portraits, 1942-1967 (Box Shared Tamiment OS008, Folder 1)
    - Executive Board Banquet, Dec 1954 (Box Shared Tamiment XOS003, Folder 1)
    - Beirne, Joseph A., circa 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Beirne, Joseph A., Jan 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Beirne, Joseph A., undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. at Inauguration of Argentinian President, circa 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. Portraits, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. with Lyndon B. Johnson and Shah of Iran, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. with Harry S. Truman, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. Shaking Hands with Lyndon B. Johnson, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Beirne, Joseph A. Speaking at Union Convention, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Conventions, 1938-1972 (Box Shared Tamiment XOS003, Folder 2)
    - Conventions, circa 1940-1952 (Flat-file-folder 3, Tray 1)
    - Conventions, 1941-1967 (Box Shared Tamiment XOS003, Folder 3)
    - Conventions, 1939-1960 (Box Shared Tamiment XOS003, Folder 4)
    - Conventions and Dinners, circa 1949-1954 (Flat-file-folder 4, Tray 4)
    - CWA Legislative-Political Conference, 1974 (Flat-file-folder 10, Tray 3)
    - CWA Shop Stewards Convention, Local 3030, Feb 1957 (Box 4, Folder 10)